http://youtu.be/lCII8lj6lDA
http://youtu.be/lCII8lj6lDA
hello again and welcome back to operations management
Rất vui được gặp lại và chào mừng đến với khóa học "Quản trị vận hành"
in our previous session's we've been talking about capacity analysis
ở buổi học trước ta đang nói về phân tích năng lực
in other words we've been thinking about what it takes to determine how
Hay nói cách khác, ta đang nghĩ về việc cần gì để xác định được một quá trình sản xuất tạo ra bao nhiêu đơn vị
many units
many units
a process can produce it generally comes down to how much time you have available
thông thường là do bạn có bao nhiêu thời gian cho resource pool
for resource pool and how much time is needed
và cần bao nhiêu thời gian
and this session we're going to work through a problem
trong bài này ta sẽ giải quyết qua các vấn đề
it may be a little bit longer than some of the other videos but please bear with
video này có thể sẽ hơi dài hơn video khác nhưng hãy cố kiên nhẫn cùng tôi
me
me
I involve I make things very very clear as to how you approach a problem like this
tôi sẽ làm cho mọi thứ thật rõ ràng để bạn có thể tiếp cận vấn đề giống thế này
here we have the LRDR  laundry company
ta có công ty giặt ủi LRDR
this company provides a commercial laundry service
công ty nảy cung cấp dịch vụ giặt ủi
to businesses whose employees wear uniforms
cho những doanh nghiệp mà nhân viên mặc đồng phục
approximately 10 percent of all loads are considered heavy loads
xấp xỉ 10% lượng hàng được xem là hàng nặng
the rest are considered normal a normal load
phần còn lại được xem là hàng thường
takes 30 minutes in the washer and eighty minutes in the dryer
tốn 30 phút trong máy giặt và 80 phút trong máy sấy
a heavy load takes 45 minutes in the washer
hàng nặng thì tốn 45 phút trong máy giặt
and 140 minutes in the dryer they have two washers
và 140 phút trong máy sấy , công ty có 2 máy giặt
and 4 dryers the washers and dryers can run 22 hours a day seven days a week
và 4 máy sấy, máy giặt và sấy có thể hoạt động 22 tiếng mỗi ngày, 7 ngày mỗi tuần
the question is can they meet their weekly demand of 500 loads
câu hỏi là liệu công ty có đáp ứng được nhu cầu hàng tuần là 500 đơn vị hàng
what we're going to do is we can to parse out this particular problem
ta cần phân tích vấn đề đặc biệt này
and identify all the key pieces of the
và xác định tất cả những mẩu tin quan trọng
information to determine whether or not we can meet the demand of 500 loads
để xác định được rằng ta có thể đáp ứng nhu cầu 500 đơn vị hàng hay không
here the grid
đây là bảng xác định 2 resource pools
that identifies the two resource pools that we have we have the washer pool
mà ta có , ta có vùng máy giặt
and the dryer pool as you can see
và vùng máy sấy như bạn thấy
we're going to be working with the amount of it's needed to
ta dùng số lượng cần để hoàn thành một đơn vị hàng giặt ủi cho cả máy giặt và máy sấy
complete a load of laundry for both the wash and the dryer
complete a load of laundry for both the wash and the dryer
are also going to look at how much time is available
ta cũng xem xét có bao nhiêu thời gian
for each of the resources so now let's go back to the original problem
cho mỗi nguồn , trở về với vấn đề ban đầu
and find the information that we need to fill in this grid
và tìm thông tin cần để điền vào bảng
in the problem they state
trong vấn đề này, công ty cho rằng
that they have two washers and 4 dryers the washers and dryers can run
họ có 2 máy giặt và 4 máy sấy , máy giặt và máy sấy
22 hours a day seven days a week
có thể hoạt động 22 tiếng mỗi ngày , 7 ngày mỗi tuần
so this is going to give us the information on the available time
điều này cho ta thông tin về thời gian khả dụng
for the different resource pools the washer
cho những resource pools khác nhau
has 2 resource units in it cus there're two washers
máy giặt có 2 đơn vị nguồn , có 2 máy giặt
each one runs 22 hours
mỗi máy hoạt động 22 tiếng
a day now an hour is 60 minutes so
mỗi ngày, mà mỗi ngày có 60 phút
each one is running 1320 minutes
nên mỗi máy hoạt động 1320 phút
so there're 2 of them the total time available per day
mà có 2 máy, nên tổng thời gian khả dụng mỗi ngày
is 2640 minutes the dryer
là 2640 phút
is also running twenty-two hours a day so each dryer runs
máy sấy cũng hoạt động 22 tiếng một ngày
1,320 minutes but there are four units in this resource pool
nên mỗi máy sấy hoạt động 1320 phút nhưng có tới 4 máy trong resource pool
so there's a total of  5280
nên có tổng cộng 5280 phút khả dụng
minutes available for dryer time now go back and look at the problem to
cho máy sấy, trở lại và nhìn lại vấn đề
find out how much time is needed
để xác định cần có bao nhiêu thời gian
we're told that 10 percent of all loads are considered heavy
ta biết rằng 10% của toàn bộ hàng là hàng nặng
and the rest are considered normal a normal load
và còn lại là hàng thường
takes 30 minutes in the washer and eighty minutes in the dryer
cần 30 phút trong máy giặt và 80 phút trong máy sấy
whereas a heavy load takes 45 minutes in the washer
trong khi một hàng nặng cần 45 phút trong máy giặt
and a hundred and forty minutes in the dryer so
và 140 phút trong máy sấy
let's go put that in the grid as well there's two forty-five minutes for the
đặt những số đó vào bảng , hàng nặng cần 245 phút trong máy giặt
washer for the heavy load and
và
140 minutes for the dryer 30 minutes for the normal load
140 phút trong máy sấy , hàng thường cần 30 phút trong máy giặt
and 80-minute for the dryer for the normal load
và 80 phút trong máy sấy
but now we have to create the average unit load
nhưng giờ ta phải tìm đơn vị hàng trung bình
this has to be a weighted average because only ten percent
đây phải là trung bình khối vì chỉ có 10%
of the load are heavy and ninety percent
hàng là hàng nặng, và 90%
are normal so I'll take 10 percent times the heavy time
là hàng thường , nên tôi sẽ lấy 10% nhân thời gian cho hàng nặng
plus ninety percent times the normal time
cộng với 90% nhân thời gian cho hàng thường
and add them together and that will give us our weighted average
và đem chúng cộng lại , ta được trung bình khối
so on average a load
trung bình, một đơn vị hàng giặt ủi
of laundry through the washer takes 31.5 minutes
mất 31.5 phút trong máy giặt
and in the dryer it takes 86 minutes
và 86 phút trong máy sấy
to this is the time we need per load
đây là thời gian ta cần trên mỗi đơn vị hàng
and we have already calculated the amount of time that we have available
ta đã tính số thời gian mà ta có
so the next step is to just calculate the number of loads per day
bước tiếp theo là chỉ tính số hàng mỗi ngày
we have the load per day
ta có hàng mỗi ngày
equally the available time for the washer which was two thousand four
bằng thời gian khả dụng cho máy giặt , 2460 phút
hundred and sixty minutes
hundred and sixty minutes
divided by 31.5 is 83.8
chia cho 31.5 , ta được 83.8
loads per day and the same thing with the dryer the total time
đơn vị hàng mỗi ngày và tính giống vậy cho máy sấy
5280 minutes divided by
tổng thời gian là 5280 phút chia cho
86 minutes needed per load giving us
86 phút cần trên mỗi đơn vị
61.4 loads per day now the question was can we meet five hundred loads in a week
ta được 61.4 đơn vị hàng mỗi ngày, câu hỏi là liệu ta có đáp ứng được 500 đơn vị hàng mỗi tuần không
so if we know how many loads per day we can
nếu ta biết được có bao nhiêu đơn vị hàng mỗi ngày
multiply it  by seven and determine the number of loads per week
ta nhân nó cho 7 và xác định số hàng mỗi tuần
the washer can meet the commitment 586.7 loads can be done
máy giặt đáp ứng được 586.7 đơn vị hàng
through the washer in a week but the dryer can't
trong một tuần, nhưng máy sấy thì không
the dryer can only do 429.8
nó chỉ có thể được 429.8
so the overall capacity of the laundry company
nên tổng năng suất của công ty giặt ủi
is only 429.8 loads per week
chỉ là 429.8 đơn vị hàng mỗi tuần
the dryer is our bottleneck it is what's driving
máy sấy là nhân tố làm đình trệ ,
our effective capacity for the process so
nó ảnh hưởng đến năng suất hiệu quả trong quy trình
the answer to your question can we meet the demand to five hundred loads per
câu trả lời cho câu hỏi có đáp ứng được nhu cầu 500 đơn vị hàng mỗi tuần không
week
week
the answer is No now and the next session
câu trả lời là không
we'll talk about how we go about determining how many
bài tiếp theo, ta sẽ nói về làm sao để xác định có bao nhiêu nguồn cần để đáp ứng nhu cầu
resources we need in order to meet their demand
resources we need in order to meet their demand
i'll see you then
Hẹn gặp lại các bạn trong bài học tới.